[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and welcome to holotalk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's show
[Music]
hi Colin how are you
yeah it's good why don't we start off
first by having you tell the listeners a
little bit about your Forum to start off
with and I would imagine there aren't
too many people who are already involved
with holography who are not aware of the
form itself
I imagine there may be some new people
to holography and some listeners that
have not visited
and there may also be some living
listeners who are not even aware of what
exactly you do on a forum an online form
so maybe you could start off in
uh tell the listeners a brief
introduction to
holographyform.org or holographyform.com
I think you have both domains don't you
no I only have dot org okay.com is uh
not available
[Music]
well you know perhaps we should start
with uh why I chose to go seek a forum
when I was learning to make Holograms
okay
I was starting to make Holograms
um everything was really challenging to
me there was Concepts I didn't
understand as far as what pieces of
equipment I might buy as well as I
didn't have a very good theoretical
background as far as what I was doing
and what I needed to do and I went out
on the internet searching for things
and found some great information on on
your form but really your website which
led me to your Forum I'm out of the
Forum business
you're out of the Forum business now
however when I was starting holography
that was the only option to actually get
a real person to say you're doing this
wrong yeah
yeah and so for me it became how I
learned the trade was to find people on
the internet and communicate either via
Forum or via a private email but I had
no way of meeting anybody other than by
contacting them on a forum yeah and and
it
what a form is on the internet and what
a forum was for me was a place to
encounter people that were either at the
same level I was or just slightly above
the level I was that were willing to
trade information
and that's what we really do at a
holography forum is we trade information
with people and there's people of every
level we have professional holographers
we have holographers that have only made
one hologram we have holographers that
have not yet made a hologram and are
still acquiring equipment it's a very
nice mix it is we're really lucky in
that regard
um at the beginning of the holography
Forum we only had people at one level
and fortunately there have been
professional holographers to adopt us
and there's been new holographers to
come in
that have made it a very what I would
call a vital place to actually explore
holography
[Music]
when I started the holography Forum
um I I made a quote that you know well
what is it that we want to do and that
is this is a place to share
and experiences about holography and
I've really
you know stroke very hard to actually
make that a reality yeah
and gosh
it's been two and a half years probably
oh really and and more than 12 000 posts
later yeah
that that we've been together and you
know it's very rewarding for me anymore
I don't get the chance to answer
people's questions
uh as much as I really just maintain the
the Mechanicals of the site and tell
people you know well if your password
doesn't burp this is why but there's so
many other people there that have more
experience than I do that that can
answer the questions that I don't need
to anymore you're actually one of the
moderators
I am uh uh I am and Michael Harrison uh
are both moderators
um
and and in a
I don't know a more fundamental sense I
actually make sure that if the Forum
falls apart that we have backups and
things like that
systems to
kind of standpoint yeah for anyone who
would be listening uh from an online
service similar to America online that
may be familiar with chat rooms
a forum could be considered a chat room
in slow motion
the fact that you're communicating back
and forth with one another but it's 24 7
in the post stay there and you reply to
them and you can go back and see what
other people have replied to and and
that's what's really nice about it is
you know you're not limited to the
people that are specifically listening
to you know at that moment but
gosh on art form I don't think I've ever
asked a question
yeah
you know that that's you know remarkable
for for such an esoteric subject as
holography to actually have that many
people focus on one spot and and we've
managed to acquire some experts in a
variety of fields you know uh Dinesh
padir is is an expert in dcg and uh uh
has done mastering for banknote
um as well as owns his own company
producing dcg Holograms and he's been
more than willing to share uh
theoretical insight as well as you know
specifics about ECG work
and then we run into people like Martin
who
polymer that he has available as
well as
dread every patent I've ever encountered
on holography and every every patent
from the beginning of photography on
every chemical process
and is very good at answering questions
about chemistry and and it's just really
interesting to see how everybody
picks their own little influence on on
uh on their understanding philography
and chooses to answer those questions I
tend to reserve my answers to questions
regarding vibration analysis and and
table design because I have 14 years
experience as a musical instrument maker
yeah
and have a lot of background in in
vibrational Dynamics and and how that
affects our work that's very interesting
that you've been able to apply that with
holography
well it's very interesting the exact
opposite problem from what I encountered
in the musical instruments yes exactly
you're trying to support by vibrations
and and in holography you're trying to
damp vibrations and then it's the exact
opposite task however all the math is
the same
that's amazing
now
anyone can come to the Forum and read
any of the posts but they do have to
register in order to make posts of their
own that's correct
correct that's right we in the beginning
we let everybody post that wanted to
come Acro come across the website but
one of the things we've learned is that
the more information that you offer
about yourself as far as
what location you're at what you're
interested in holography are the uh the
more
we can offer you and so I I do require
people to register but
whoever get from them is their email
address yeah and anything else they
offer is really up to them yeah so if
someone wants that's listening to this
wants to become an active member of The
Forum you'll have to register but you
can
to holographyform.org and go through all
the posts and even an archive of post
yes every every post is available
um the original posts you can no longer
reply to
um we started at a company called
Network 54.
[Music]
all of those posts be archived over
um I'm very very fortunate uh who've had
the help from a user who uses the name
Hollow M
um to he wrote some scripts that allowed
us to import all of those scripts wow
those all of those posts and uh were
able to actually access those and search
those with our search parameters
um
it brought for technical reasons we
chose not to allow anybody to reply to
them yeah we want we'd rather have
somebody start a new post on the same
subject okay now you've you've actually
grown much Beyond just an informal group
of
internet and enthusiasts that are
posting a form and have become more of a
formal group with what I believe is the
porcelain group is that correct oh yeah
that was kind of an odd thing that just
happened spontaneously where one day we
were all saying you know it's fun
talking on the internet but we'd really
like to meet each other and we'd really
like to share some of the things we've
been working on in person because you
don't get a chance to understand the
personalities that are involved until
you actually sit in a room with somebody
and you know share a coffee or share a
pint of beer and and say hey you know
what is it about you why is it that you
want to be involved and
and we decided that hey why don't we get
together don't we meet
we needed a name for we needed a name
for this group that was going to
Encompass more than Technical holography
and more than artistic holography but
also something that was brand new
something that uh that you really built
the the foundations of and that was
amateur holography as a group yeah and
and we really wanted to to get together
and say
you know what we can be outside of spie
what we can really do is build something
that is simply holography and simply
here to to disseminate information and
and then
came up as the porcelain cat Group which
is
sort of an odd little derivation from uh
Graham saxby's book practical practical
holography where he
where he's linked had as his test object
for every new setup he's doing I
actually used a porcelain cat for my
first hologram you know it's funny my my
first Holograms were all a porcelain dog
it I don't know if you've ever seen the
uh RCA logo versus dog listening to a
phone yeah yeah I I have a fault Shaker
that is that dog and that was
that was a test object for years and
then one day I decided it was too shiny
and now I have a partial in cat oh I see
okay
uh tell us a little bit about your
get-togethers I understand they've
become a little bit more formal than
just having a cup of coffee and you have
individual members that will choose
specific topics and give presentations
the other members
members yes each of us uh really have
our own little uh
uh vectors that go off into our research
and and you know I guess and that's true
of any hobby and
one of the things we decided was that
the ways to entice people to come
together and and to share the
information that they have was for each
of us to make a
semi-formal
location I don't know if I call quite
call it a formal presentation of what
we've been working on and uh at the
first the meeting there's only been two
we you know requested anybody who might
have something to talk about to make a
formal presentation and we each put
together formal presentations at the at
the meeting the lectures were
were amazingly enlightening as far as
how much research people have actually
done into things and and the tangents
that each of us have taken were so far
away from the others of us have been
that that it was remarkable and we
scheduled two days worth of these
lectures and when we got to the second
day we just kind of looked at each other
and said
get into the lab and let's make some
Holograms and we ended up dividing off
into two groups one group
silver halide work in the other groups
that did some dcg work and we're bounced
between the two groups and and really
came up with some very fun Holograms
really learned a lot about what was
going on
one of the groups I ended science
mastering the silver halide hologram
um
which turned out uh to be to Michael
Harrison ended up making copies of I did
a transmission
Michael Harrison made copies of which
became gifts for all of us that attended
oh that's nice yeah it was it was really
very nice it was really fun I got to
work with a holographer who had been
working you know mostly in isolation and
he didn't know any of just the random
tricks that you know for me like seemed
obvious like he was measuring all of his
Bean paths from the first Bean splitter
whereas I'd only measure one beam path
you know or two beam paths rather from
each beam splitter and it was saving me
time and I was using a piece of string
as opposed
tape measures which which is what's the
first thing that's obvious but a piece
of string is actually a lot faster yeah
and there were some other things like he
was
calculating the uh focal length of his
collimation mirror
um
whereas I would just take a piece of
paper and measure the diameter of the
mirror and hold it back as
a spatial filter until the illumination
filled that mirror
great
um and you know there were just little
tricks like that that we all got to
share
well I really admire the fact that you
you and your folks were able to put that
together because it's something that I
had been thinking about doing
contemplating doing and even even
started to launch ideas on getting
something like that together years ago
and I just failed at doing it I think
basically what it did it did to with me
is it allowed me to uh say you know what
you've got to take a look at your
strengths you have to take a look at
your weaknesses and you have to
acknowledge both and there's nothing
wrong with acknowledging weaknesses
and and putting something together like
that for me was just something that I
couldn't do so it's glad that you guys
were able to do that
well in
you know what for us we have 125 members
we have 25 members that I would say are
looking at every post every few hours
and and what we actually decided was
that all of us have our weaknesses but
as a group
we could concentrate on our strength and
put it together yeah you know I there's
no way in the world I could have put
together a group of people uh uh to make
a meeting like that happen yeah it's
just not possible
um you know for me as an individual but
a group of us we were actually able to
each divide it up into the tasks that we
could do yes Michael Harrison was so
instrumental in putting together the
first meeting he he you know really
took it on as as a task hosted it that
was at his home is that correct yeah in
his home with his lab and and just did a
wonderful job of it and you know it's
fun to talk to him now about it because
at the time we're thinking my gosh
Michael's doing such a great job and the
way he describes it is two weeks before
this event happened I wasn't sure if
anybody was going to show up
foreign
and you know we're new and and it is the
beginning of of something that I hope
will become become a great thing
holography is
complicated now of having places to show
big art exhibitions
or anything or anything we you know we
have we have some wonderful artists that
have been
that have been years now that are
producing what I think is fantastic work
but nobody knows about it nobody has a
way to find it and we have some
wonderful artists that have only been
around for two years that are producing
fantastic work I think so too and I
think and I but I don't think they're
getting the lessons of the old artists
yeah and I'm hoping that
eventually that maybe two or three years
from now when you come to a
repeat that what you're doing is you're
meeting not only you know the
holographers that are part of
photographyforum.org but you're also
meeting the holographers that that
for 30 years that that have have a huge
body of work that just want to show
their newest things and and and and are
excited still about holography you know
holography in the 80s was such an
exciting thing you know I wasn't able to
be a part of it because you know I
wasn't around then I was wasn't I was
too naive to know how exciting it was
but there was
from industrial backers that everybody
was excited about it and and in the 90s
it just kind of fell apart you know the
the big development in the 90s was the
diodes and and how you know literally
for a hundred dollars now somebody can
put together a lab and make Holograms
yeah and they can take a diode laser and
and and make that happen and nobody knew
that
what about your own work what have you
been doing with some of your projects
well my latest uh little addition to my
shop is I've I've decided that
that the future of my holographic work
is true color holography
and it is uh overhead reference being
I've been working horizontally for a
really long time and as a theatrical
lighting designer I love playing with
lighting with my object lighting
um and the only way I can really do that
and and and
get it into my head in the same way that
uh theatrical lighting Works has
so my newest table now is four feet by
eight feet
thick of aluminum honeycomb
all made out of scrap honeycomb out of
Boeing and with a three foot tall Gantry
above it that that runs my whole
reference beam I now have a 50 milliwatt
red diode that I'm using as well as a
100 milliwatt uh coherent 315m DPSS
laser so I've got the red and green
aspects of my three color system that
I'm just trying to decide now what I'm
going to do about blue blue eff is just
remarkable
when you can get it in the coherence
length but it's also thirty thousand
dollars yeah
that's my ultimate goal there's some
people around that have been finding the
uh blue DPSS
that emit beams out of both ends of the
cavity and
you can use those you get about 100
Watts out of one beams
um and you can find them for about three
thousand dollars if the diode array has
burned out yeah but the diode array is
about four thousand dollars to replace
yeah
still very expensive I can't decide what
I'm going to do I I you know go back and
forth where one day I say oh I'm gonna
have to get a blue DPSS because 473
nanometers is just
some ci1 and then I look around and I
say you know for thirty five hundred
dollars
and a lot of infrastructure into my lab
I can get an argon laser yeah so I
haven't quite come up with a solution
for
um and we still we still need patience
you know with this field absolutely
and and that's I guess the
understatement of a lifetime Frank is
that uh uh not only do you need patience
but you need just an infinite amount of
patience I've had so many just random
things go wrong with that takes forever
to figure out like the
that my processing baths wasn't quite
right and I wasn't getting the the
results that I've been you know if I
look through my notes all the results
are right but I'd never bothered to
measure the temperature in my processing
baths is this with dcg or silver
spin silver yeah and all of a sudden one
day my lab is at 60 degrees and
nothing's developing this time and I
keep increasing my exposures now I'm
over exposing under developing and I'm
getting bad results yeah
funny all of the things that crop up you
know I when when I'm dealing with
newcomers and I'm sure you've dealt with
way more newcomers than I have
one of the things that comes up
immediately is the patients it takes to
make stability happen yeah
the level of stability we need to make
long exposure Holograms is just
phenomenal and it's so loud so outside
of the realm of common experience that
it amazes me that anybody figures it out
much less than I did yeah
well you're doing nice work now you also
have a section of that holography form
where people can show the work that
they've created as well right yeah
there's a gallery there it really
requires you to have uh some Internet
space that you can store your work on
and link to
um I haven't really gotten it to the
point it's something I would like to do
in the future but I haven't gotten it to
the point where you can just say hey
this is a photo on my hard drive I want
to show it
and you can upload it and I and I
actually pay for the hosting space for
those photos yeah and and also also the
transmission of them as well so you have
to take that into
probably have a limit on how much data
you can trans per month I imagine right
I I do have a limit but worrying you
know I The Forum costs about twenty
dollars a month to host yeah and we're
using about 100th of our bandwidth okay
there's a huge amount of space in that
regard and I'm not really concerned
about that you know fortunately uh
two months somebody comes along and says
hey you know I really value what you're
doing and I really want to support you
and they you know there's a link on the
on the splash page of site that allows
you to send me twenty dollars to support
the forum for a month and it turns out
that I end up paying for about a half of
it and the people that come to the site
end up paying for about a half of it and
I'd like to encourage everyone to click
on that link and send you uh twenty
dollars for the 2005 season that you're
coming up on well that would be one way
sure you know you know more than than
the actual money I would love the people
to to just show up and share the work
and get excited about holography because
you know it's our excitement is amateurs
that's going to take biography
through the years yeah it's not going to
be any big corporate sponsor it's not
going to be anything it's it's really a
really us as amateurs that are that are
going to carry holography through yeah
yeah and that's how it's been actually
and and there's how it's been since the
80s there's been there's been a lot more
excitement I think of course I may be
prejudiced to this but I I think there's
a lot
more excitement in amateur holography
that's happened in the last 10 years
than any other aspect of life
well I you know and I hope that's true I
I look at you know the dot matrix
Holograms that are coming out now and I
look at the work that uh Lydia's doing
with her high-end Holograms and and you
know I look at the work that you're
doing as an amateur or I don't know
calling you an amateur is quite the
right word I'm a professional amateur
you're the most experienced amateur how
about if we say that you know
um
your equipment your seconds away from
doing the level of work that Lydia's
doing and you know it it
you're exploring all of those uh LCDs
and all of that work and
you're what what separates you from
Lydia they're trying to make a living at
it and you're just trying to disseminate
it to people who who just want to you
know be fascinated by it and explore it
yeah and I and I think that's what make
Holograms exciting yeah I have all those
little mini portraits
that I I put the process up on the
website I have all those of my kids and
they're they're one of my biggest
Treasures as they continue into
adulthood now to look back at those
well and you know portrait work is
stunning it's it's remarkable I I
when you started you had a little Forum
that you started that uh uh was sort of
designed to teach everybody how to do
portraits yeah which went nowhere well
unfortunately yeah and and probably My
Fault by not doing what you do with
yours as far as being a good moderator
once again recognizing a weakness well I
I don't know if I I think you're
shortchanging yourself I I think
it is
was really good it sort of inspired the
beginning and I think a lot of people
are working along that that line and I
wish there was better
better than amongst the individuals that
are actually
walking down that road at this point and
one of the things that's come up is uh
we would love to have you host us
because
more to show than any of us oh I don't
know you might come out here and say oh
my God I can't believe I spent money on
airfare to go to this guy's place uh you
know serious it's not going to be how it
is at all
you know I'd love to come and meet
everybody
well you know what would that what that
says to me is that the next meeting
needs to be on the East Coast because we
need to have you attend thank you you're
one of the most gifted people that uh I
think we could ever have lecture to us
thank you you know I don't I don't fly
and that's really cut a lot of
opportunities for me you don't fly uh I
flew for the first time because I I
I I wanted to finally do it and I flew
for the first time only two or three
years ago which would have made me oh
I'm going to be 49 so it would have made
me maybe about 47 years old the first
time I got on a plane
went up to Boston because I figured it'd
be a quick trip from Philadelphia only
like in 90 minutes or something and the
trip there was exhilarating you know the
takeoff I never experienced such power
in a jet and everything it was really
great but then on the way back there
were grounded flights because of severe
thunderstorms and
flight back was absolutely I I swear to
God I thought I was going to die I
thought we were all gonna die and it was
the worst 90 minutes of my life and that
was it that was my first and only flight
that I will ever take ever
that's it I'm done well I'll drive
anywhere I drive down to Florida you
know I mean it doesn't the last trip I
did down to Florida I did it 16 hours
straight you know I love to just put it
on cruise and listen to talk shows and I
take extra time to drive
California is too far for me to drive
though it's a long trip out to
California from where you are we're
running on uh on fumes here as far as
time to keep this file size Matt able
for people because believe believe it or
not there are quite a few people that
are still on dial-up connections that
access this so I try and keep the the
show within a reasonable amount of time
is there anything that you want to add
that we have
talked about yet
you know the thing that I would add is
I'm not sure if it's come across in in
the private Communications that that you
and I have had but you are personally
the reason why I am involved in
holography and it was encountering your
website that got me started in
holography after 20 years of being on
the back benches of just reading about
the technology
you your website website of research
you've done I would still simply be a
poor person hoping to one day make a
hologram well I'll take that to heart
thank you very much I appreciate that
I don't know it's a very very nice
compliment and I I appreciate you making
it and I I do believe that your own
contributions to amateur holography for
students for those it would be like you
see those magazines uh popular
photography or whatever I think you're
doing the exact same thing only with
holography
maybe it's time to pass the torch
you know what I mean I'm an old man now
you know I'm not a young guy anymore
like you guys I see the pictures of you
guys you're all young guys
you know so you know what we're doing
though is we're spreading the torch it's
not yet time to pass the torch I'm I'm
still giving you 40 more years to
contribute to this field yeah I'm still
honest I still have a good bench press
so I'm not going anywhere too soon but
uh all right I'm going to close and
probably head up to bed shortly okay
I know we've rambled on and given you
way more information oh it was great it
was it was great to finally have some
time to chat because you know we've
we've known each other for a while and
we've sent a couple emails back and
forth but as far as actually chatting I
don't think we've really had the
opportunity to do what we did tonight
and I'm thankful for it